{
  "reference_number": "12445",
  "clauses": [
    {
      "question": "1. What process should the Government use to set a new emissions reduction target in legislation?",
      "question_index": 0,
      "answer": "The Government sets a 2050 target in legislation now",
      "answer_index": 0,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "2. If the Government sets a 2050 target now, which is the best target for New Zealand?",
      "question_index": 1,
      "answer": "Net Zero Emissions - Net zero emissions across all greenhouse gases by 2050",
      "answer_index": 1,
      "notes": "I support most ambitious, clearest, science-based target. We need to reduce all greenhouse gases, including methane. Applying two\n\n baskets thinking to our 2050 target, the most ambitious and impactful approach would be to achieve negative long-lived gas\n emissions, while reducing short-lived gas emissions to sustainable levels. Getting to this point would mean that New Zealand is\n\n contributing to global cooling."
    },
    {
      "question": "3. How should New Zealand meet its targets?",
      "question_index": 2,
      "answer": "Domestic emissions reductions only (including from new forest planting)",
      "answer_index": 7,
      "notes": "The clearest approach is a “firewall” which separates international contributions from our domestic Zero Carbon Act targets. This\n would not stop New Zealand from purchasing international carbon credits as an additional contribution to global mitigation efforts."
    },
    {
      "question": "4. Should the Zero Carbon Bill allow the 2050 target to be revised if circumstances change?",
      "question_index": 3,
      "answer": null,
      "answer_index": 5,
      "notes": "The 2050 target should only be revised in exceptional circumstances. The purpose of the Zero Carbon Act is to provide\n\n accountability, certainty and flexibility. It will provide accountability and certainty by setting clear, legally-binding emission reduction\n targets. It will retain flexibility by permitting different governments to use different policies to meet these targets, in response to\n changing circumstances and new technology."
    },
    {
      "question": "5. The Government proposes that three emissions budgets of five years each (i.e. covering the next 15 years) be in place at any given time. Do you agree with this proposal?",
      "question_index": 15,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "6. Should the Government be able to alter the last emissions budget (i.e. furthest into the future)?",
      "question_index": 4,
      "answer": "No - emissions budgets should not be able to be changed",
      "answer_index": 9,
      "notes": "No. Budgets should only be revised in exceptional circumstances. It is not appropriate for a new government to “have a say” on an\n upcoming budget which has already been set. This would create too much uncertainty and instability. What a new government can\n do is introduce different policies to meet the upcoming target"
    },
    {
      "question": "7. Should the Government have the ability to review and adjust the second emissions budget within a specific range under exceptional circumstances? See p36 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 5,
      "answer": null,
      "answer_index": 5,
      "notes": "Under exceptional circumstances, yes. For example, it might be appropriate to change an upcoming budget after an extreme natural\n disaster (such as a major earthquake). Revising a budget in this situation would not mean changing the long-term 2050 target. To\n\n provide maximum certainty and accountability, budgets should not be revised unless the circumstances are exceptional"
    },
    {
      "question": "8. Do you agree with the considerations we propose that the Government and the Climate Change Commission take into account when advising on and setting budgets? See p44 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 6,
      "answer": null,
      "answer_index": 5,
      "notes": "I generally agree with the proposed list of considerations to take into account when setting emission budgets: scientific knowledge\n\nabout climate change technology relevant to climate change economic circumstances and, in particular, the likely impact of the\ndecision on the economy and the competitiveness of particular sectors of the economy fiscal circumstances and, in particular, the\n\nlikely impact of the decision on taxation, public spending and public borrowing social circumstances and, in particular, the likely\nimpact of the decision on fuel poverty energy policy and, in particular, the likely impact of the decision on energy supplies and the\n\ncarbon and energy intensity of the economy the government’s obligations under the Treaty of Waitangi the three government\nobjectives for climate change policy: sustainable economy, global and local leadership and creating a just and inclusive society"
    },
    {
      "question": "9. Should the Zero Carbon Bill require Governments to set out plans within a certain timeframe to achieve the emissions budgets?",
      "question_index": 7,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "This time frame should be 6 months after an emission budget has been set."
    },
    {
      "question": "10. What are the most important issues for the Government to consider in setting plans to meet budgets? For example, who do we need to work with, what else needs to be considered?",
      "question_index": 8,
      "answer": null,
      "answer_index": 5,
      "notes": "The Government’s policy plans to meet emission budgets should be comprehensive, fair, cost-effective, environmentally sustainable,\nand reflect a commitment to Te Tiriti o Waitangi."
    },
    {
      "question": "11. The Government has proposed that the Climate Change Commission advises on and monitors New Zealand's progress towards its goals. Do you agree with these functions? See p42 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 9,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "The Commission should not be a decision-making body"
    },
    {
      "question": "12. What role do you think the Climate Change Commission should have in relation to the New Zealand Emissions Trading Scheme (NZ ETS)?",
      "question_index": 10,
      "answer": "Advising the Government on policy settings in the NZ ETS",
      "answer_index": 6,
      "notes": "The commission should not make final decisions. Otherwise it risks being a compromised watchdog."
    },
    {
      "question": "13. The Government has proposed that Climate Change Commissioners need to have a range of essential and desirable expertise. Do you agree with the proposed expertise? See p45 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 11,
      "answer": null,
      "answer_index": 5,
      "notes": "I generally agree with the proposed list of expertise which should be collectively held by the Climate Commission: climate change\npolicy (including emissions trading) resource economics and impacts (including social impacts, labour markets and distribution) te\n\nTiriti o Waitangi, te reo me ona tikanga Māori and Māori interests climate and environmental science including mātauranga Māori\nexperience with addressing adaptation challenges like planning, insurance and local government risk management engineering\n\nand/or infrastructure community engagement and communications. public health"
    },
    {
      "question": "14. Do you think the Zero Carbon Bill should cover adapting to climate change?",
      "question_index": 12,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "15. The Government has proposed a number of new functions to help us adapt to climate change. Do you agree with the proposed functions? See p47 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 13,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "16. Should we explore setting up a targeted adaptation reporting power that could see some organisations share information on their exposure to climate change risks?",
      "question_index": 14,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "Do you have any other comments you'd like to make?",
      "question_index": 16,
      "answer": null,
      "answer_index": 5,
      "notes": "I would not like my name to appear in the summary of submissions that the ministry may publish\n\n\n\n\n You have elected to withhold your personal details from publication."
    }
  ]
}
